This is the first in a series of videos
that are going to be working through parts of the
process modeling components of this workshop.
This workshop was initially offered as
a 4-day workshop
where the first 2 days are very coding-intensive
where we're working through
very scripted exercises.
Those are available on our website.
The second 2 days with this workshop
involve more lecture materials.
And those don't have an accompanying script.
So for anyone who is interested
in working through these materials
and understanding the material that
we cover during these lectures,
we're recording these lectures after the
fact and making them publicly available.
So the overview of the entire
day's worth of material is
a lecture on the theory and
motivation underlying process modeling
and then illustrating that using the example of
Hubbell's neutral theory of biodiversity.
There's then several exercises
that we worked through as a group,
getting some experience working with
and thinking about the neutral theory.
and seeing how that works
when we mess with the parameters,
and how to implement that in R.
I'll be recording lectures
and making them available
on the theory and motivation of process modeling
and the example of Hubbell's neutral theory
and then coming back as we do at
the end of the day to talk about
the general approach of recovering
parameters from the results of model simulations
using neutral theory as an example.
So the first topic is coming into this
general conceptual space of what we're
referring to as process modeling and
getting a sense for exactly what we
mean by this and how it might
apply in ecology and evolution.
So let's look at 3 specific questions.
What do we mean when we're talking about
something called the process model.
And then what are the potential applications
for process modeling for specifically
ecological and evolutionary dynamics?
And then what are the limitations
of an approach like this?
We can get excited about the strengths and it's
also important to come into things
with eyes open about the limitations.
So what do we mean by process modeling anyway?
And a question to ask yourself
and a question that's helpful to
think about is what comes up for you when you
think about the notion of the process model.
You may have done a whole bunch of
simulation modeling on your own.
Or you may have no idea. And either one is great.
In this context, when we
talk about a process model,
I like to say it's essentially just a game.
in which we are
exploring some phenomenon of
interest as a game that plays out
according to a series of rules.
How that game plays out is going to depend on
both the sort of set of rules that we identified
and maybe some tunable parameters
that we modify in our rules.
and then there's often an element of stochasticity
or chance.
So these or may not be deterministic
at either large or small scales.
Hubbell's neutral theory is actually a really
great example of a process model that has been
hugely influential in community ecology.
Even if you may or may not think of yourself as
somebody who has dealt a great
deal with simulation or process
modeling in general,
if you have some familiarity with the
neutral theory, that's a process model.
We're also going to be using neutral theory in the
rest of the workshop as an
example of a process model
that's relatively
constrained and in its set of rules
and relatively intuitive to look at
the results and see what's going on.
We'll then build up in the second day
of materials which are available on
the website to interacting with
more elaborate process models
that still have neutral theory as kind
of an underlying conceptual framework,
but are building in much more functionality
and many, many more processes.
So when we set up a process model,
there are a few things to keep in mind.
One is that whatever set of
processes or games that we set up
they could be really straightforward
or they could be really complex.
And even what seems like a relatively
simple set of rules can turn out to be
really complex in terms of different
ways the outcomes can play out
or in terms of the
amount of computational power required
to explore the behavior of the model.
Often, what we'll find in a
process model as I've mentioned
is that the outcomes aren't
strictly deterministic.
It may not be that we run a model
with the same set of parameters
and the same set of rules and we get
exactly the same outcome every time
just in the way that maybe you play
game of tic-tac-toe against your cousin
and sometimes you are going to end up with one
arrangement of things and another time you're
going to end up with another another
arrangement of the X's and the O's.
And finally, these models are not necessarily,
solvable analytically in the way
that other modeling approaches.
often are, especially in ecology and evolution.
When we think about how we
interpret a Lotka-Volterra model
we're often solving for right moments
when the system is stable or solving
for how this system will even out equilibrium.
In a process model, it may be
difficult or impossible to find
a closed form or asymptotic solution
for how the model is going to play out
and that's fine
because that's not what we focus on when we
focus on the outcomes of a process model.
It's also worth saying that
sometimes it is possible to
solve one of these models,
especially if we take a limit of infinitely large
periods of time or infinitely large systems
these often have asymptotic solutions or
consistent emergent outcomes
that kind of transcend the minutiae
of what's going on at small, scales.
So here is just an opportunity to think
about some of the potential applications
of a process modeling approach
in ecology and evolution.
And here's a whole bunch of them.
I'm gonna talk them through a little bit.
Being able to set up a system
of rules that describe a process
that we're interested in and
then observe how those rules
play out to produce outcomes that
we may be interested in is a really
flexible and really powerful,
tool to have in our toolbox.
It's especially good for when we want to
explore a phenomenon that involves some of these
traditionally, potentially really
intractable or really challenging
components.
In particular, we may be
interested in a set of processes
that play out over really long
temporal scales over really large
portions of space over
really large spatial scales.
and those models are going to be exploring
something that we couldn't necessarily
get at by running an experiment.
Maybe we're interested in how all of the species
ever have evolved and we just don't have time to
run experimental evolution
across all of Earth's history.
Or maybe we're curious about, really large scale
biogeographic phenomena that can't be addressed
in the real world.
We can also use this when we're
interested in processes that
fall into the general space of
what we can call complex systems
which are characterized by many interacting
components that often generate feedbacks and
have interactions and outcomes that come
out at different levels of organization.
Or are context dependent, where
how some sub process plays out
varies depending on the state of the system.
And this is basically all by biological systems
if we're going to be realistic about things.
And of course, often when we're trying to generate
a theoretical model to understand the system
we abstract away some of this complexity.
We abstract away some of this context
dependence. And that's great, right. That's fine.
That's how we arrive at insights. And
sometimes we would like to be
able to incorporate more layers
of this complexity into a modeling approach.
And process models have more flexibility to
incorporate this complex or variable set of rules.
This doesn't mean that it's
a silver bullet of course
there's a limit to how much
complexity we can build in or how much
Insight we can gain from a model that can trade
off with the level of complexity that it involves.
So let's think about some use cases for
process modeling in ecology and evolution.
One of the first uses cases is to
do some scenario exploration when
we have some understanding of how a process works
and we want to do some exploration of
what the outcome of that process might be
if we were to change
some parameter or rate,
change something about the inputs of a
process to see how the outcomes change.
Another really powerful
application for process modeling
that is really well exemplified by
Hubbell's neutral theory
is as a sort of a null or neutral model.
How would we expect the system to look at random?
How would we expect a potentially complex
interacting set of processes
to play out in the absence
of some mechanism or some
force that we're interested in?
And then comparing that to what
we're observing in real data or
observing in other simulated data
to get a sense for how these mechanisms that
we are potentially interested in exploring
manifest in a system when we can't necessarily
guess a priori how we would differentiate
between the effects of this mechanism and
what we'd expect to see if this
mechanism weren't operating.
As we talked about earlier,
another possible use case
is to explore huge swaths of time and
space that vastly exceed what we're
able to explore empirically or experimentally.
Or if we want to explore parallel universes:
to think about how a system would look
in a thousand years under, for example,
different scenarios of climate change.
We can run different simulation
models and mess with the climate
change parameter and see how things turn out.
And the last example is the potential use of
a process model to start to rule
out possible generative processes
that may or may not be consistent with
what we observe in the real world.
So for example, if we have observed a
pattern in the real world, like for example,
a hollow curve species abundance distribution,
And we have a few ideas about
potential generative models,
generative processes that could
have created this pattern..
We can formalize those in the
form of process models that
play out those processes in excruciating detail
and then compare the outcomes that we
get from these simulation models to the
patterns that we're actually
observing in the real world.
And this one is not necessarily a
positive affirmation that we have
guessed the correct process if
the outcome of a model matches
what we observe in the world.
But, it can be really useful to help us
rule out potential generative mechanisms
that really don't give us things that
match what we're saying in the real world.
And these are of course just a few potential
applications that I'm talking about here.
I would invite you to take a minute to think
about, daydream about, potential applications
for this kind of approach in whatever
your area of interest or expertise may be.
And the last thing before we dig
into talking about a process model,
neutral theory,
is taking a moment to think
about some of the limitations
or on the box warnings about using process models.
Number one is that in order
to really understand and
appropriately interpret the results
that we get from a simulation model,
we need to have
a fairly rigorous understanding
of the underlying rules that define that model.
It may be that the system of rules or
processes that are built into a model
may or may not be a reasonable approximation  of what is happening in the system of interest.
For example, we're going to
be working a lot with a model
that uses what's called a birth death
process with a fixed community size.
In this case we have a ecological
community of, say, a hundred individuals.
And these individuals will die and be reborn,
but the number of individuals will never change.
And that constraint of a
fixed number of individuals
has some really important implications
for how the model behaves,
especially when that number is really small.
And that may or may not be a
reasonable assumption that we make
that we can then use to transfer our
results to how we think about real systems.
Maybe, a small island that does have a
really fixed amount of resource availability
can be reasonably modeled this way
But, if we are in a system where the amount of
resource availability or primary productivity
is fluctuating a lot
Maybe that fixed number of individuals
assumption is going to introduce things
that really drive us away from the
thing that we're trying to model.
Another one that is always changing,
and also always a constraint,
is the reality of limits on computational power.
We can be really smart about
how we code up a process model,
but the fact is these are always going
to be more computationally intensive
than something that we can
solve with a single equation.
And depending on the level of complexity
or the number of processes
or the amount of stochasticity
that we build into a model,
the computational resource demand
that that model requires can increase.
(sometimes terrifyingly quickly!)
This has historically been a constraint
on the whole process modeling approach.
If you don't have a computer and you're
having to run one of these by hand,
you're going to be able to do a lot fewer
simulations than if you have a computer.
But even now that we have computers,
we do have to be mindful about
what it is that we are building into our model
and whether or not that's going to be a feasible
request of the available resources.
At a more philosophical level
we have to be mindful that pattern
or successfully reproducing a pattern
via a process model
does not necessarily mean that the
way that we produced that pattern
is an accurate representation
of the processes that actually
generated that process out in the world.
For example, if I were to
observe that the 10 people
sitting around me in a restaurant
the 10 people I'm happening
to eat dinner with that night,
I could come up with a story,
a backstory for each of these individuals
that would tell me the processes
in their lives that led them to
be at this dinner table tonight.
And all of the story lines
would end with that person coming to this
restaurant and being at this table tonight.
But maybe I don't know anything  about these people
and maybe I've just made some stuff up
and it happens to get me to the right answer.
That doesn't mean that my
stories that I've told myself
about how they got there
are correct about the underlying
processes that led them there.
Long way of saying,
that just because we've managed
to successfully reproduce
something that we're observing in nature
doesn't mean that the mechanisms
that we use to get there
are the right mechanisms to
explain what's happened out there.
And there's a variety of ways to get around this
or to become more specific
about what kinds of epistemological questions
are we asking with a process model
and how are we interacting
with data and different sources of evidence
to leverage these models.
For now we'll just say we need
to recognize that pattern is
not the same thing as process.
That these models can't always
be fully diagnostic about generative processes.
And finally, is the concept of
what's called model identifiability.
This can be an issue with complex or simple models,
but really comes out with really complex models.
Eventually it can occur that
multiple different sets of rules
or multiple different combinations of parameter settings
will get us to functionally indistinguishable results.
When we have many different
models that generate results
that we can't tell apart
that really limits our ability
to use the results to infer
what has happened at the generative stages to produce these results.
When we're interacting with a process model
we want to keep these  considerations in mind because they are
really important for us to be
able to interact with these models in
an appropriate way as practitioners.