So our last section is going to deal with the process and high level conceptual architecture
of inferring the parameters that we use in a process model given the results of that model
using neutral theory as an example.
And specifically we're going to be dealing with the question of what do we mean by inferring parameters from outcomes and why would we want to do this.
We're going to walk through an example of using this approach using neutral theory.
And then we're going to use that as an opportunity to talk about some of the challenges that we run into using an approach like this.
This is largely set up for doing a much more involved machine learning procedure on these types of data,
which we approach in the second day of this workshop.
And again, the materials for that part of the workshop are available on the website.
And if you're having trouble understanding the high level motivation for those materials, this may be a really useful lecture for you to listen to.
So what do we mean by inferring parameters given the outcomes?
This is important to have a clear sense of what exactly we're accomplishing here.
We are going to use the outcome of a model to guess at the parameters that produced it.
To do this, we do need to make the assumption that the processes that are baked into a model -
- so in the example of neutral theory, the birth, the death, the probability of speciation, the probability of immigration -
are a reasonably accurate description of the processes that generated the data that we are working with,
whether those data come from some other theoretical model, from simulation modeling or from the real world.
This could be a really big assumption.
It comes back to what we talked about in the first lecture about the importance of understanding the rules and structure of a process model so that we can be responsible about how we interpret the results.
However, assuming that the proceses we've got in the model are a reasonable description of the processes that are relevant to our data,
we can use our knowledge of how the model behaves over large ranges of parameter space
to try and guess at the parameter settings that might be responsible for a specific outcome that we observe.
This is the whole heart of what we call likelihood free inference,
which is the topic of the tutorials in the next day of the workshop.
So let's get a little bit clearer sense of what we're talking about here.
The overall procedure is: we're going to get a clear sense of how the model behaves over a huge range of parameter settings.
And so we're gonna run many, many, many simulations over a huge chunk of the range of possible combinations of parameters.
So we're gonna use a whole bunch of different combinations of M and Nu and J for neutral theory.
And we're going to use those simulations to produce a database of how the outcome variables,
so the Hill numbers calculated with different values of q,
relate to the parameters that we used to generate them.
Then we're gonna formalize that knowledge by fitting models.
We're going to be using machine learning models, random forests.
Of the form "parameters ~ the outcome variables".
So put that another way, we're going to train a machine learning model using the hill numbers
to predict the parameter combinations that produce different combinations of hill numbers for the results.
And then we can use this trained machine learning model to guess at the parameter values that were used to produce observed outcomes.
So then if we have a set of hill numbers that we got from another model
or from the real world, or anywhere,
we can use those, combined with this trained machine learning model,
to estimate the parameter values that may have produced this combination of Hill numbers.
So let's go over this workflow using neutral theory.
We're going to be predicting m, the immigration rate, and Nu, the speciation rate, from the general structure of a neutral theory model.
The first step is going to be to run a whole bunch of simulations over a range of parameters.
For this, we're going to keep the meta community and the local community size equal, and we'll keep the number of time steps equal.
But we'll sample over a huge range of combinations of parameter values for the immigration rate, M and the speciation rate, Nu.
So here we're varying M from 0.6 to 0 and we'll vary Nu also from 0 to 0.6.
Every one of these points in this plot represents a combination of migration rate and speciation rate
that we are using to run this model.
So this is 10,000 pairs, 10,000 combinations of immigration and speciation rates.
And if we run these, we'll end up with a data set that looks like this.
We have the parameter values that we use in a simulation as a set of inputs and then the results  that were produced by those inputs as the Hill numbers.
And it's worth taking a second to look at how these different outcome variables
relate to variation in the parameters that are used to generate them.
Here we're looking at heat maps of how the Hill numbers vary over combinations of the immigration rate and the speciation rate.
What we see are these really interesting gradients where it's clear that as we increase either immigration or speciation
we end up with, for example, greater species richness.
You can see how these are not totally deterministic models, right?
They're sort of fuzzy gradients, but they are consistent over large scales.
They're going to show this general pattern emerging.
You can also see, and we'll get back to this later,
what almost look like isoclines within these gradients
where we can actually get similar values for the hill numbers
with different combinations of parameters.
So for example, we can get this dark blue color is with, like, no speciation and very high immigration (.2)
or we can still get those values in a scenario where we have no immigration but relatively high speciation.
And this is foreshadowing a little bit of that model identifiability problem that we talked about before.
We break this down to what we're going to be putting into the machine learning model.
We're going to be trying to predict, for example, the migration rate M.
from the Hill number. When we do the actual model we'll be using all of the hill numbers, but for visualization we're going to use just one.
And again, we can see that there's clearly correlation between the hill number and the immigration and speciation parameters.
There's also a fair amount of noise in this relationship.
Just knowing one of the hill numbers
is not enough information for us to exactly pinpoint the migration rate or the speciation rate.
But we can get a general trend.
So I'm not going to in this lecture go into the details of how random forest models work.
For now, I will say that we are fitting these using a random forest because you can think of it as a very flexible form of regression
in that we don't need to know, a priori, the shape of the relationship between the predictor variables and the outcome variable,
but we can leverage whatever relationship there does exist to fit essentially a very flexible regression.
And this is a gross oversimplification, but is a high-level description of what we're trying to accomplish here.
So we can fit this random forest model in which we are predicting the migration rate from the 3 hill numbers
using the data that we generated by running a whole bunch of simulations.
And if we examine this regression, we can see a decent approximate R squared.
And this is telling us that it's a random forest model.
And then if we examine the model accuracy, again,
we see something that we might have been able to guess at
based both on heat map plots that we showed and looking at that one dimensional or single predictor regression earlier.
Which is that there is a relationship between the migration rate and the Hill numbers,
and that we can do a pretty good job of recovering migration rate given the parameters.
That is, the predicted values on the y-axis are a reasonable approximation of the actual values, which are on the x-axis.
If it were perfect they would all fall along this yellow 1:1 line.
And we see that there's some pretty good predictive capacity,
but also there's a lot of misses in this data
because again perhaps there's not enough information given just the Hill numbers to uniquely identify the migration rate.
We can run through the same process predicting Nu.
And we see a better but similarly sort of fuzzy relationship.
So given these models that we have predicting the parameters given the outcomes,
we can go ahead and run an experiment or play out a game
where we're going to generate some new data using the same model simulation framework
and see how well we can recover. the parameters that we used to generate these data.
So this is some code that you can run in R using the functions that are included in the online materials
to run a new set of simulations using a never before seen combination of migration and speciation rate.
And then to compare the predictions from the random forest models to the actual data.
So to be more specific, to test how well we can guess our new combination of parameter values based on the results of those models.
by using the random forest that we trained on our big data set to estimate the parameters that generated the outcome variables that we provided.
And so for example, we can see that, one time when I ran this, we tried
a migration rate of .32 and a Nu of .43.
And then we ask the random forest model to predict, based on the hill numbers that we got,
what was the value for M and what was the value for Nu that were used to produce these data?
And it guessed .28 for M and .37 for Nu which is ballpark but not perfect.
And yeah, the estimation is good, but it's not perfect. And this cycles us back to one of the challenges of estimation.
It's not necessarily the only thing that's going on here
but a really important one when we're dealing with these process models
is this question of model identifiability, or the lack of statistical leverage for identifying the generative parameters
when multiple combinations of parameters can give us the same results.
So as we've seen you can have different combinations of Nu and M and you can arrive at the same or similar values for the different Hill numbers.
Which makes it difficult to use the Hill numbers to be precise about what the generative values for M and Nu were.
So how could we get better traction on a problem like this?
Well, there's a few options and this is really foreshadowing the next day of the workshop.
But one of the first ones is to have different sets of parameters
or different sets of model processes
that better capture the data that we're interested in modeling.
We can also build in more complex models that allow us to take advantage of
more types or more dimensions of data about a system.
This is in many ways - the procedure that we've outlined here is in many ways similar to trying to
guess what city you're in based only on the temperature reading.
A city in Florida and a city in Texas may have exactly the same temperature reading
and so it's really difficult to tell which city you're in based just on the temperature.
But if we could add more data dimensions,
for example, maybe something about humidity,
we might have a much better chance at guessing where we are in the world
based on these 2 data points
than just on the one data point or one data dimension.
So if we're able to build a model, a process model is able to take into account and take advantage of
more different dimensions of data or more ways of looking at a system,
we can often get much better traction on it than we can by looking at just a single dimension.
And this is the motivation for what we call the MESS modeling or RoLE modeling framework
and it's going to be the main focus of the next sections of the workshop.
So to summarize what we've covered today, in principle, we can use process models
to infer the parameters that generated observed data
provided the observed data are generated by similar processes to the model.
And that there are a few things few things that can really complicate this process
including efforts at what's called out of sample prediction -
So if we were trying to guess it parameters when we've never seen those before -
model identifiability -
And, again, these wider concerns or considerations with process models
including the computational effort required to run the model
and the underlying validity of the modeling rulebook given what it is that we're trying to model.
And staying tuned for the next sections of the workshop,
we are going to be talking about considerably more flexible and multi-dimensional biodiversity models
and ways to operate those at scale using the iBioGen and MESS frameworks.
Those are the next day's worth of materials, which are available on the course website and are a great resource for learning more about this.