Okay, so now we're going to discuss process modeling within the framework of Hubbell's neutral theory.
And if you're not familiar with Hubbell's neutral theory, it's fully called the Unified Neutral Theory of Biodiversity and Biogeography.
And it's a process model that describes how the diversity of ecological systems can change over time according to a very simple set of rules.
So we're going to discuss UNTB (which is how we'll refer to neutral theory) as a process model.
Then we're going to get into the specific rules of neutral theory and the outcomes that we pay attention to.
And this will set us up to play the game interactively.
We can do this with a set of die, or coded up as a set of functions in R.
Those pre-written functions are available on the course website.
So the Unified Neutral Theory has a fundamentally process modeling approach. In it, we're looking at a set of entities, which are ecological communities,
That are made up of a fixed number of individuals. So like the trees in the forest. And as the model plays out, individuals die, give birth,
immigrate (or arrive in the system from outside the system) and speciate into new species according to a set of rules and parameters.
And the outcomes of neutral theory are what I kind of call semi-deterministic in that the specific outcome of any given single run of this model
can't be predicted with detail - but that it exhibits dependable, consistent behaviors. Given enough runs with the same set of parameters,
we can be confident that we're going to end up with a general set of patterns that are consistent with what we have seen before.
So let's talk about the rules and then the outcomes of neutral theory.
The structure of a neutral model, or if a process model in general, is that we have a  playing field, or the board of the board game,
we have the set of rules or processes by which the model proceeds
and then we have a set of outcomes that are what we pay attention to and interpret as the model results.
In neutral theory the playing field has 3 parts.
Mostly we focus on this piece in the middle, the local community.
I like to use the example of a patch of garden plot in your backyard.
Your garden plot in your backyard has some number of spots where things can grow.
And so the local community has a consistent size over time.
And it's made up of different species of things that are growing in your garden.
We also have the meta community which I like to describe as your whole backyard
or maybe your whole neighborhood
and all of the plants that are growing in your backyard or your neighborhood.
The meta community acts as a source of new species that may land in your local garden plot
or land in the local community and might start growing there.
And lastly we have - this is largely a bookkeeping piece but we do to keep track of it -
All of the species that we have ever had occur in our model.
And this may be different from all of the species that are still present in the system by the end of the model
because in neutral theory species can go extinct,
And so we have to keep track of everything we've ever seen
because we may not still be seeing it by the end of the model.
Okay, so the process.
What happens in a neutral model?
So the defining feature of each time step in a neutral model is
an individual from the local community has to die.
They are then replaced either through what's called a local birth -
which is to say one of the other individuals in the local community has an offspring -
or via immigration,
which would be when an individual from the wider meta community has,
you can think of it as a seed or a juvenile that arrives in the local community and takes up living there.
Sometimes in this birth process, a speciation event can occur.
The individual that establishes in the local community is of a never before seen species that is different from the parent species.
In the real world you can think of this as a mutation event where the offspring is now a new species separate from the parent.
And then this just repeats.
And it can repeat for a set number of time steps.
Often with neutral theory we'll repeat it until the model has reached some state that we can define as an equilibrium.
And it can be tricky to define an equilibrium in a process model,
but for our purposes here, we'll say we can run it until it stops sort of changing a whole bunch.
And so neutral theory has a series of parameters that can be used to modify the outcomes of the model.
These are the number of individuals in the meta community or the size of the meta community
and the number of species in the meta community.
You can imagine that if there's only one species in the whole meta community,
it's gonna be hard to get diversity in the local community drawing from that meta community.
At the local scale, we have also the number of individuals that are present in the local community.
For this little toy visual, that's there's 5 individuals in the local community.
This parameter can also be really important.
You can get sometimes more idiosyncratic behaviors with very small local communities.
And it can become much harder computationally model as you have a really huge local community.
Then there are 2 more parameters that we can  tune like dials in a radio and explore how changing those parameters affects the models behavior.
And those are, the probability of an integration event occurring.
So M.
This is the probability that when a new individual is born, that individual's parent is coming from the meta community.
And if the individual's parent is not coming from the meta community, it's what we call a local birth.
So the individual's parent is coming from the local community.
And lastly we have the parameter Nu.
Which is the probability that when that birth event occurs,
whether the parent is from the meta community or from the local community,
the probability that that birth event is also a speciation event
where the offspring is of a different species than its parent species
and it's a new species that we have never before encountered because it has never existed before.
So let's work through the process in a little bit more exacting detail.
Every time step, the first thing that happens is an individual is chosen at random to die.
The probability of any particular individual being the individual who has to die
is going to be 1 / however many individuals there are
because every individual has an equal probability of dying.
That's part of what makes this a neutral model.
By losing the orange individual here, we have created a gap in the local community
and we need to fill that slot by having a birth event
and filling that slot in with a new individual.
We need to have either a local birth event or an immigration event to start to fill in this slot.
So again, we'll roll the die.
With probability 1-M,
that birth event will be a local birth where the parent is chosen at random from the local community.
And if it's a local birth event, every individual in the local community
has an equal probability of being the lucky parent.
Again, this is neutral. No individual has a leg up and any other individual
around winning the birth lottery.
And the other way this can happen is if it's an immigration event
so with probability M
a parent individual is chosen, again at random,
from the meta community.
Again, no individual in the meta community has any advantage over any other individual in winning that lottery.
Finally, before we can fill in that slot with our new individual,
we do have to check if there's a speciation event happening at this time step.
With probability Nu, the birth will not simply be a new individual of the exact same species.
It will be a new individual of a novel species.
If that happens, we need to update the species of the offspring to a brand new species
and we have to make a note in our all-time species list
that we have added a brand new species to the all time list.
And if there's no speciation, we don't have to bother with any of that.
Once we've worked through these, like, decision trees,
we can replace the individual who died with this new baby individual in the local community.
And then we're gonna do that indefinitely
or until we've iterated over all the time steps that we're going to iterate over.
And so, say we've run this a whole bunch of times, then what do we do?
Well, we're going to want to be looking at the outcomes of this model and
with neutral theory we're interested in - or, for now, let's say, since there's many applications of neutral theory -
but we're going to look at  the diversity and structure of that local community after we've run this model for a while.
So we can take the local community.
And a common way of looking at abundance
which you'll be very familiar with if you've worked through the previous 2 days of this workshop
is to plot what's called a species abundance distribution,
which is a means of visualizing how diversity is distributed within a system.
So for a quick primer, if you've skipped the past couple of days or just want a primer on species abundance distributions...
Here we've plotted on the x-axis the rank of species in the system
if we rank them from the most to least abundant.
And on the y-axis we plotted how abundant each species is.
This plot is telling us that the very most abundant species in the system has 3 individuals.
That's the green species.
And the second most abundant species has one individual. And so does the third.
Those are the blue and the purple species.
When we have a more realistically sized community with more species and more individuals
the shape of this distribution can tell us a lot about the structure of a system
whether we've got a whole bunch of species and they're all relatively equally abundant
or whether we have maybe still a whole bunch of species but really all of the individuals
are accounted for by one really, really abundant species.
And so the shape of the species abundance distribution tells us a lot about community structure.
We can also quantify this evenness and diversity using what's called Hill numbers.
For more information on Hill numbers, I encourage you to look at the materials from the previous two days of the workshop
because we work through applications of Hill numbers to all sorts of different biodiversity data, including abundance data like this.
For now we can say that if we calculate the Hill number
it's a diversity index that will capture different aspects of this species abundance distribution
based on this parameter q.
A hill number that's calculated using the parameter q of 0 is going to give us species richness.
And if we use q values, increasing q values, so q = 1 or q = 2
we're going to be shifting the amount of weight that we put on
the shape of the species abundance distribution.
And we're going to be taking into account more and more of the presence and representation of rare species in the system.
At this stage in the workshop, we worked through the neutral model a few times using an
interactive hands-on approach of a whiteboard and running the die.
If you would like to play that game a few times on your own,
we've got this slide that you can refer to.
It can be informative to work through this manually by choosing parameters for J, M, and Nu
and then playing through the cycle a few times.
There are also materials available on our website for running code
to play neutral games on your own computer.
And we'll link to those materials along with these video lectures
so that you can gain a little bit of intuition for how the neutral model behaves.